♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease, worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave, you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance, the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 43=
=ตอนที่ 43=
Ruoqing.
รั่วชิง
I almost killed Qiu Ziliang
หานเยว่คราวนั้น
when I worked together with Han Yue.
ข้าเกือบจะฆ่าฉิวจื่อเหลียงได้แล้ว
I could've killed him.
เดิมทีข้าสามารถทำให้เขาตายได้
I still lost in the end.
ข้าก็ยังแพ้อยู่ดี
General Han's sacrifice was in vain.
แม่ทัพหานเสียสละชีวิตไปเปล่า ๆ
Qiu Ziliang is still alive.
แต่ฉิวจื่อเหลียงกลับยังมีชีวิตอยู่
I should've known.
ข้าควรจะรู้นานแล้ว
He is a devil.
ว่าเขามันเป็นปิศาจ
I must make use of every chance I have
ขอเพียงมีโอกาสเพียงน้อยนิด
to strike him down
ข้าก็ควรจะคว้าไว้
and finish him off.
จู่โจมเขาให้ตาย
How could I
ทำไมข้าถึงปล่อยให้เขา
let him make a comeback?
ล้มกระดานแล้วเริ่มใหม่ได้
Ruoqing.
รั่วชิง
It was my fault.
เป็นข้าที่ทำร้ายท่าน
Xiu got hurt because of me.
ทำร้ายอาซิว
So did Ruoling.
ทำร้ายรั่วหลิง
I've brought harm to all of you.
เป็นข้าที่ทำร้ายพวกท่านทุกคน
It wasn't your fault.
ไม่ใช่ความผิดของเจ้า
It was.
เป็นความผิดของข้า
My arrogance led me here.
เป็นข้าที่เอาแต่ใจตัวเอง
It was all my fault.
เป็นความผิดของข้าทั้งหมด
Ruoqing.
รั่วชิง
Trust me.
เจ้าเชื่อข้านะ
There is still hope.
ตอนนี้ยังไม่อับจนหนทาง
Qiu Ziliang was indeed in isolated meditation.
ก่อนหน้านี้ฉิวจื่อเหลียงกำลังปิดด่านจริง ๆ
But the medicine he made had some issues.
แต่ยาอายุวัฒนะที่เขาหลอมขึ้นมีปัญหา
Was it my uncle's doing?
เสด็จอาทรงวางแผนใช่หรือไม่
Yes.
ใช่พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
He worked on it with the divine healer.
รวมถึงหมอเทวดาผู้นั้นด้วย
Before that,
ก่อนหน้านั้น
Qiu Yanzhi and Cheng Xi
ฉิวเยียนจือกับเฉิงซี
managed to divide
ทำให้ทัพเสินไฉของเขา
the Shencai Army.
ต้องแตกเป็นเสี่ยง ๆ
They made him believe there was a mole.
ทำให้เขาเชื่อว่ามีไส้ศึกแฝงตัวอยู่
To draw the mole out,
ดังนั้นเพื่อล่องูออกจากโพรง
he used his isolated meditation as a cover
จึงจงใจแกล้งปิดด่าน
and sent the Left Chariot on a secret investigation.
และให้จั่วเช่อลอบตรวจสอบอย่างลับ ๆ
So the Left Chariot
ดังนั้นจั่วเช่อ
came back to the Capital a long time ago.
ความจริงกลับเมืองหลวงไปแต่แรกแล้ว
Yes.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
He's been hiding in Gao Ping's home.
เขาซ่อนตัวอยู่บ้านของเกาผิงมาตลอด
What answer
แล้วเขาตรวจสอบ
did he get from the investigation?
ความจริงอะไรได้บ้าง
Prince Guang,
อ๋องกวง
Qiu Yanzhi, and Ling Ling
ฉิวเยียนจือ และยังมีหลิงหลิงอีกคน
have been exposed.
ทั้งหมดถูกเปิดโปงแล้ว
But you are not exposed, Your Majesty.
ทว่าฝ่าบาทยังดีพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
We've been cautious
ก่อนหน้าพวกเราทำงาน
so far,
ก็ระมัดระวังมาตลอด
and they haven't suspected us.
ไม่ได้กระตุ้นความสงสัยของเขา
Prince Guang has been planning
ตอนเกิดเรื่องเจาลู่
since the Morning Dew Rebellion.
อ๋องกวงก็วางแผนทุกอย่างไว้
He might have started even before that.
หรือกระทั่งอาจจะวางแผนไว้ก่อนหน้านั้น
He managed to fool all of us.
เขาปกปิดได้ลึกล้ำมาก
My teacher
อาจารย์ของข้า
once commented on Prince Guang's wisdom.
ยามมีชีวิตเคยวิจารณ์เสด็จอาอ๋องกวง
He said Prince Guang was cautious and mindful with speech,
บอกว่าเขาสุขุมพูดน้อย
and had the quality of great wisdom.
ต้องฉลาดหลักแหลมมาก
A man with great wisdom
และเป็นที่ชาญฉลาด
would surely have great ambitions.
ย่อมมีปณิธานใหญ่
But why would he thwart Cheng Xi's plans
แต่ทำไมเขาต้องขัดขวางเฉิงซี
time and time again?
ครั้งแล้วครั้งเล่า
Why would he save your life?
ทั้งช่วยฝ่าบาทซ้ำแล้วซ้ำอีกด้วยล่ะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
He loves and cherishes
เพราะเขารักถนอม
his own reputation.
ชื่อเสียงของตัวเองยิ่ง
I'm nothing like him.
ข้าแตกต่างจากเขาโดยสมบูรณ์
To get where I am today,
ข้าเพื่อให้บรรลุจุดประสงค์
I became the godchild of an evil man,
รับโจรเป็นพ่อได้
I usurped the throne,
ฆ่าอาจารย์ชิงบัลลังก็ได้
and I became loathed by the world.
รับคำด่าทอจากคนทั่วหล้าได้
But he's different.
แต่เขาไม่เหมือนกัน
Guang means jade.
เขาคืออ๋องกวง
There can't be any stains on jade.
เขาต้องบริสุทธิ์ไร้ราคี
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
At this point,
เรื่องมาถึงขั้นนี้แล้ว
we should proceed with the next step.
ก็สมควรเริ่มต้นก้าวต่อไปแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Official Li has
ทางใต้เท้าหลี่
everything in place.
เตรียมการพร้อมสรรพแล้ว
He awaits Your Majesty's final order.
เพียงรอให้ฝ่าบาทรวบแห
But I...
แต่ข้า
I am worried about Ruoling.
ข้ายังเป็นห่วงรั่วหลิงมาก
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
It's a critical time.
ตอนนี้เป็นช่วงเวลาสำคัญนะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Don't let emotions ruin the plan.
จะทำอะไรด้วยอารมณ์ไม่ได้
She knew I had let the Wang family down.
ทั้ง ๆ ที่รู้ว่าข้าผิดต่อตระกูลหวัง
Yet, she still risked her life for me.
แต่นางกลับยินยอมบุกน้ำลุยไฟเพื่อข้า
I owed her
ชั่วชีวิตนี้
too much for this lifetime.
ติดค้างรั่วหลิงมากเกินไปจริง ๆ
That's because
เพราะนางรู้ว่า
she knew how her grandfather died.
ท่านปู่ของนางตายเพราะเหตุใด
Your Majesty, when you win,
มีแต่ฝ่าบาททรงได้ชัย
all of this suffering
ทุกข์ยากลำเค็ญทั้งมวล
will truly be over.
จึงจะยุติลงอย่างแท้จริง
(If you win,)
(เจ้าชนะ)
(Xing empire prospers.)
(คือต้าซิงอยู่)
(If you lose,)
(เจ้าแพ้)
(Xing empire is doomed.)
(คือต้าซิงสลาย)
(Tell me)
(บอกข้าสิ)
(that you can do it!)
(ว่าเจ้าทำได้)
(Yes.)
(พ่ะย่ะค่ะ)
Greetings, Prince Guang.
คารวะท่านอ๋องกวง
Prince Guang,
ท่านอ๋องกวง
I'm glad you are here.
ท่านอยู่ที่นี่ก็ยิ่งดีแล้ว
Duke Chu wants you
ใต้เท้ากำชับมาแล้ว
to see the bride off as her family.
ให้ท่านส่งเจ้าสาวในฐานะครอบครัวฝ่ายหญิงพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Miss Qiu, I can see you've been busy.
แม่นางฉิวช่างเป็นผู้สูงส่งกิจธุระมากจริง ๆ
Even now, you still aren't groomed.
จนตอนนี้ยังไม่ได้แต่งเนื้อแต่งตัว
Did you forget you have a wedding today?
หรือลืมงานอภิเษกในวันนี้ไปแล้วหรือพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Listen up, everyone!
พ่อแม่พี่น้องฟังให้ดี
His Majesty's wedding is today.
วันนี้เป็นวันอภิเษกของฝ่าบาท
The ban on wine has been lifted.
วันนี้ไม่ต้องงดสุรา
He granted us fine wine
พระราชทานเหล้าชั้นดี
so we could celebrate it for him.
แบ่งปันแก่ประชาชน
There's enough for everyone!
ทุกคนมีหมด
Come on!
มา มา มา
Line up and get your wine!
เข้าแถว รอรับเลย
(It's already)
(ถึงวันอภิเษก)
(the day of their wedding.)
(เร็วเพียงนี้แล้วหรือ)
Come on.
มา มา มา
There's enough for everyone.
มีกันครบทุกคน
(I can never)
(สุรามงคลประเภทนี้)
(enjoy a wedding wine like this.)
(ดื่มไม่ลงจริง ๆ)
Here's yours.
ถือให้ดีนะ
- Next! - Okay.
- คนต่อไป - จ้ะ ๆ
Yan Xiu?
(เหยียนซิว)
Yan Xiu is in love with Yanzhi.
(เหยียนซิวชมชอบเยียนจือ)
But Yanzhi is marrying His Majesty.
(เยียนจือกลับแต่งจะกับฝ่าบาท)
Come on!
มา
There's enough for everyone!
ทุกคนมีกันหมด
Line up and get yours!
เข้าแถว มา
Come on!
มา มา มา
Hold your wine.
ถือให้ดีนะ
Here's yours.
ถือให้ดี
Scram!
ไสหัวไป
People like you don't deserve
สุรามงคลของฮ่องเต้
to have His Majesty's wine!
พวกเจ้าคู่ควรดื่มหรือ
Get lost!
ไสหัวไปเดี๋ยวนี้เลย
All of you, get lost!
ไสหัวไปให้หมด
There he goes again.
มาอีกแล้ว
I'll never pity
ทำไมข้าถึงสงสาร
a man like you.
คนประเภทนี้ได้นะ
These are all mine now.
เป็นของข้าทั้งหมดเลย
How dare you steal my wine! Get him!
กล้าแย่งเหล้าของพวกเราหรือ อัดมันเลย
Forget it.
ช่างเถอะ
Consider I've avenged Madam Li.
ถือเป็นการล้างแค้นให้ท่านอาลี่แล้วกัน
Stop it.
อย่าตีเขา อย่าตีเขา
All of you, stop beating him.
ทุกคนหยุดมือนะ
Cut it out!
อย่าตีเขาเลย
(Left Advisor)
(จั่วซื่อ)
He's an official!
เขาเป็นเจ้าหน้าที่ทางการ
Leave, quick!
ทุกคนรีบสลายตัวไป
Leave!
สลายตัวเร็ว
Everyone, leave!
สลายตัวไปให้หมดเร็ว
I can never enjoy
สุรามงคลประเภทนี้
a wedding wine like this.
ดื่มไม่ลงจริง ๆ
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
♪Who else will swim in the deep end♪
♪ผู้ใดจะว่ายแหวกลงไปในน้ำลึก♪
♪When the wind and rain empty the long scale♪
♪เมื่อลมฝนทำบันไดยาวร้างเปล่า♪
♪Who will still go to work early and return late after being drenched♪
♪ผู้คนเปียกฝน ยังนุ่งดาวห่มจันทร์♪
♪Some have longings♪
♪มีคนอาลัย♪
♪Some have decided to leave♪
♪ก็มีคนตัดใจ♪
♪We can't see clearly during the day♪
♪สิ่งที่มองไม่ชัดล้วนอยู่ยามกลางวัน♪
♪With no arguments, there are no lies♪
♪ไร้คำแก้ต่างก็ปราศจากคำลวง♪
♪But the battlefield didn't teach me to distinguish between them yet♪
♪ทว่าสนามรบไม่เคยสอนข้าให้แยกแยะ♪
♪Who says I never made a wish♪
♪ไยข้าจะไม่เคยอธิษฐาน♪
♪Who says I was once missed♪
♪ไหนเลยจะไม่เคยถูกคิดถึงเช่นกัน♪
♪Old sorrows aren't at rest♪
♪ทุกข์เก่าไม่จางหาย♪
♪Getting nightmares♪
♪ฝันร้ายเข้ามาแทรก♪
♪Let's see if love or hate disintegrate first♪
♪เฝ้าดูรักหรือแค้น สิ่งใดสลายก่อน♪
♪The vicissitudes of life where I'm wandering♪
♪ชีวิตผันผวนพเนจร♪
♪Are full of barriers without you♪
♪เมื่อไร้เจ้า อุปสรรครายล้อมกาย♪
♪Even hypocritical words♪
♪แม้หน้าไหว้หลังหลอก♪
♪And the far distance♪
♪หนทางยาวไกล♪
Greetings, Your Highness.
คารวะพระนาง
♪Can't let us meet in vain♪
♪ล้วนมิอาจเฉียดกายโดยเปล่า♪
♪I'm supposed to be in your fleeting years♪
♪เดิมข้าอยู่ในกาลผันผ่านแห่งเจ้า♪
♪An empty room for a hollow goodbye♪
♪ห้องหับว่างเปล่า เมื่อว่างพบกันใหม่♪
♪The world is fainting, a true love's meeting♪
♪ฟ้าดินพร่ามัว♪
♪Even nightmare will end when it's time♪
♪สักวันฝันร้ายย่อมสิ้นสลายหายไป♪
♪I had been missed♪
♪ไหนเลยจะไม่เคยถูกคิดถึงเช่นกัน♪
♪The melancholy hasn't ended, a new nightmare begins♪
♪ทุกข์เก่าไม่จางหาย♪
♪Will love perish or will it prevail?♪
♪เฝ้าดูรักหรือแค้น สิ่งใดสลายก่อน♪
♪The drifter's eternity♪
♪ชีวิตผันผวนพเนจร♪
♪My world falls apart without your presence♪
♪เมื่อไร้เจ้า อุปสรรครายล้อมกาย♪
♪Even hypocritical words♪
♪แม้หน้าไหว้หลังหลอก♪
♪And the far distance♪
♪หนทางยาวไกล♪
♪Can't let us meet in vain♪
♪ล้วนมิอาจเฉียดกายโดยเปล่า♪
♪I'm supposed to be in your fleeting years♪
♪เดิมข้าอยู่ในกาลผันผ่านแห่งเจ้า♪
♪Life scattered like a shower of leaves♪
♪ชีวิตอับเฉาราวผการ่วงโรย♪
♪A heavy heart doesn't go far♪
♪ยิ่งหนักอึ้งยิ่งยากลอยไกล♪
♪Even the Moon♪
♪จันทร์สกาวบนฟ้า♪
♪Loses its glimmer♪
♪ย่อมมีทั้งแรมเพ็ญ♪
♪But love prevails above all♪
♪ทำอย่างไรรักจึงยิ่งแข็งแกร่ง♪
♪Like the lost time we failed to hold on♪
♪ดีกว่าปล่อยเวลาให้สูญสิ้นไป♪
(Chess of Generals Camp)
(สำนักหมากรุก)
Move out!
ยกเกี้ยว
Seeing things
เห็นทางด้านพวกเจ้า
are going smoothly for you,
ดำเนินการได้อย่างราบรื่น
I feel relieved.
ข้าก็สบายใจแล้ว
It's them again.
เป็นพวกเขาอีกแล้ว
An order from the Chess Overseer.
ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกมีคำสั่ง
There's been a change in plan.
แผนมีการเปลี่ยนแปลง
Hunt down Ling Ling,
ตามโจมตีหลิงหลิง
and execute her.
พบแล้วฆ่าทันที
Yes!
ขอรับ
Yanzhi will never want me dead.
เยียนจือไม่มีทางฆ่าข้าแน่
What exactly happened?
ที่แท้เกิดเรื่องอะไรขึ้นกันแน่
Sir!
ใต้เท้า ใต้เท้า ใต้เท้า
Pursue him!
ตามไป
Take him out!
ฆ่าเขา
Yes!
ขอรับ
You got everything you wanted.
ทุกสิ่งล้วนสมปรารถนาเจ้า
Congratulations.
ยินดีด้วย
Dismiss.
พวกเจ้าออกไป
His Majesty and I are going to bed.
ข้าจะปรนนิบัติเอง
Yes.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Going to bed?
ปรนนิบัติ
Qiu Ziliang ordered me
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงสั่งหม่อมฉัน
to give you a Crown Prince as soon as possible.
ว่าต้องให้กำเนิดรัชทายาทแก่พระองค์โดยเร็ว
You even have power over
ช่างควบคุมสายเลือดมังกรแห่งต้าซิง
the royal bloodline of the Xing empire,
ไว้ในมือได้จริง ๆ
Duke Chu.
ฉู่กั๋วกง
So...
ดังนั้น
I need a child.
หม่อมฉันต้องการลูกหนึ่งคน
I'm afraid
ข้าก็อยู่ในสารรูปนี้แล้ว
I'm in no shape...
เกรงว่า
I can't grant you that request.
เกรงว่าคงจะร่วมมือกับเจ้าไม่ได้
In that case,
ในเมื่อเป็นเช่นนี้
I shall take my leave now.
หม่อมฉันทูลลาก่อน
Wang Ruoqing.
หวังรั่วชิง
I know
ข้ารู้ฐานะ
your true identity.
ที่แท้จริงของเจ้าแล้ว
I beg your pardon?
ฝ่าบาททรงหมายความอะไรนะเพคะ
My identity?
ฐานะอะไรเพคะ
Aren't you Wang Ruoqing?
หรือเจ้าไม่ใช่หวังรั่วชิง
If you want me to be,
หากฝ่าบาททรงต้องการ
I can be her.
หม่อมฉันก็เป็นได้เพคะ
Just as the time Han Yue needed me to be.
ก็เหมือนตอนหานเยว่ต้องการครานั้น
If I was Wang Ruoqing,
หากหม่อมฉันเป็นหวังรั่วชิง
I would...
หม่อมฉันก็จะ
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Well?
เป็นอย่างไร
Was it her?
ใช่นางหรือไม่
It's the second time
บ่าวเฒ่ายืนยันตัวตนของแม่นาง
I've come to confirm her identity.
ท่านนี้มาสองครั้งแล้ว
She looks like her.
หน้าตาคล้ายมากจริง ๆ
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
If you want to confirm
หากทรงต้องการพิสูจน์
if she really is Ruoqing,
ว่านางคือหวังรั่วชิงหรือไม่
there is still another method.
ความจริงยังมีอีกวิธีหนึ่งเพคะ
What do you have in mind?
เจ้ามีวิธีอะไร
Miss Ruoqing was afraid of cats when she was little.
ตอนเด็ก ๆ คุณหนูใหญ่หวาดกลัวแมวมาก
Whenever she saw a cat,
หลังจากเห็นแมว
she got rashes over her body.
ร่างกายก็จะขึ้นตุ่มพุพอง
But her sister Miss Ruoling
แต่ตอนเด็ก ๆ คุณหนูเล็ก
loved cats.
ชอบแมวที่สุดเพคะ
So Miss Ruoling could only
ดังนั้นตอนคุณหนูเล็กยังเด็ก
play with cat doll.
จึงเล่นแต่แมวปลอม
Little Bell.
เสี่ยวหลิงตัง
That's right.
ใช่ ใช่ ใช่
That's the doll's name.
ก็คือตุ๊กตาแมวตัวนั้นแหละเพคะ
Its name was Little Bell.
ชื่อของมันคือเสี่ยวหลิงตัง
Sir.
ใต้เท้า
Li Deyun met with the scholars after returning.
หลังจากหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋นกลับจวนก็ลอบพบลูกศิษย์
The group of seven discussed
เจ็ดคนพูดคุยปรึกษากัน
more than an hour before leaving.
ครึ่งชั่วยามจึงแยกย้ายขอรับ
What did they discuss?
พวกเขาคุยอะไรกันหรือ
We don't know yet.
ตอนนี้ยังสืบไม่ได้ขอรับ
Sir.
ใต้เท้า
Should we interrogate some of them?
จะให้จับสองสามคนมาลงทัณฑ์เค้นถามหรือไม่ขอรับ
Do not alert the enemy.
อย่าแหวกหญ้าให้งูตื่น
Keep tabs on them.
จับตาดูพวกเขาไว้
Let's see what Li Deyun has
ดูว่าหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
up in his sleeve.
ตกลงแล้วจะมาไม้ไหน
Yes.
ขอรับ
Did you get the divine healer?
จับหมอเทวดาได้หรือยัง
We got everyone
นอกจากจั่วซื่อ
except the Left Advisor.
คนอื่นจับได้หมดแล้วขอรับ
Good.
ดี
Dismiss.
เจ้าออกไปก่อนเถอะ
Yes.
ขอรับ
I'm still alive.
ข้ายังไม่ตาย
Are you disappointed?
เจ้าผิดหวังมากใช่หรือไม่
You will die sooner or later.
เป็นเรื่องที่ต้องเกิดขึ้นสักวัน
So,
บอกมา
what is the solution?
วิธีแก้คืออะไร
This is your design,
ในเมื่อเจ้าเป็นผู้วางแผน
so you must know a way to undo it.
เจ้าต้องรู้วิธีแก้แน่
There is no solution.
ไม่มี
Qiu Ziliang,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
your demise is nigh.
เจ้ารอความตายเถอะ
Tian Shan.
เถียนซ่าน
I came here to sincerely
ข้ามาขอโทษเจ้า
apologize to you.
ด้วยความจริงใจ
I found out today
วันนี้ข้าเพิ่งรู้ว่า
that your family
ครอบครัวของเจ้า
had died by my hands.
ตายด้วยน้ำมือของข้า
But that was ten years ago.
แต่นั่นมันก็เป็นเรื่องสิบปีก่อนแล้ว
Drop the act.
อย่ามาเสแสร้ง
You have no regard for human lives.
เจ้ามันมารร้ายที่ฆ่าคนเหมือนมดปลวก
You will die a horrible death.
เจ้าต้องไม่ตายดี
You will certainly die a horrid death!
เจ้าต้องไม่ตายดีแน่
Tian Shan.
เถียนซ่าน
You got my apology.
ข้าก็ขอโทษไปแล้ว
What you said
เจ้าพูดแบบนี้
was a little hurtful.
ข้าไม่ชอบฟังเอาเสียเลย
Do you still have relatives on your wife's side?
ทางบ้านแม่ของเจ้ายังมีญาติอยู่ใช่หรือไม่
How about this?
เอาเช่นนี้ดีหรือไม่
For every day you refuse to tell me,
หนึ่งวันเจ้าไม่พูด
I'll kill one of them.
ข้าก็จะฆ่าหนึ่งคน
If you keep your mouth shut for two days,
สองวันไม่พูด
I'll kill two of them.
ข้าก็จะฆ่าหนึ่งคู่
I can take my time with you.
พวกเราก็ค่อย ๆ ยื้อกันไป
Let's see who wins in the end.
ดูว่าใครจะยื้อได้ถึงที่สุด
Qiu Ziliang!
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
Qiu Ziliang! You're a demon!
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงเจ้ามันเป็นมารร้าย
You're a heartless wretch!
เจ้ามันเป็นเดรัจฉานชั่วช้า
Teacher.
อาจารย์
What is my uncle's motive?
ที่แท้เสด็จอาต้องการอะไรกันแน่
The throne?
บัลลังก์
The world?
แผ่นดิน
Or the prosperity of the Xing empire?
หรือว่าต้าชิงที่เจริญรุ่งเรืองจริง ๆ
I can't
ข้า
see through his mind.
มองเขาไม่ทะลุแม้แต่น้อย
If he bears ill intentions for me,
หากเขามีเจตนาร้ายจริง
then how should I
เช่นนั้นข้า
deal with him?
สมควรลงโทษเขาอย่างไร
Do I put him in jail?
ขังเขาไว้
Do I release him?
ปล่อยเขาไป
Or must I take his life?
หรือว่าฆ่าเขา
♪Life is a dream, how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪In the windy rain, where will my heart settle?♪
♪ลมพัดฝนหล่น ใจนี้จะหยุดลงที่ไหน♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Fate can't do anything about the bleak bonds of this world♪
♪วาสนาอับเฉา ไหนอาจฝืนชะตา♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
The pain I suffered in this life
ความทุกข์ในชาตินี้ของข้า
is unspeakable.
ไม่อาจบรรยายได้
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
But meeting you
ทว่าการพบเจ้า
was the mercy and greatest gift
คือสวรรค์นั้นสงสารข้า
Heaven had given me.
ประทานสิ่งที่ข้าชมชอบที่สุดมาให้
Ruoling.
รั่วหลิง
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪If love was but a dream, how long would it last?♪
♪ความรักเหมือนความฝัน จะคงนานสักเท่าไร♪
♪A cold night with a lonely drink♪
♪ราตรีอันเดียวดาย ดื่มความช้ำเพียงลำพัง♪
♪The heat is intoxicated, but the shackle remained♪
♪ชูจอกรดราด มิอาจคลายปมในใจ♪
♪Entering the dream with clarity, going ashore with your company♪
♪ขอฝันอย่างเป็นสุข เป็นเพื่อนหยุดใจดวงนี้♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
His Majesty arrives!
ฝ่าบาทเสด็จ
Your Majesty is still recovering.
ฝ่าบาทประชวร
There is no need to visit me.
ก็ไม่ต้องมาเยี่ยมข้าหรอก
Grandmother.
เสด็จย่า
The rite must be upheld.
ธรรมเนียมไม่อาจละทิ้ง
Greetings, Grand Empress Dowager.
เยียนจือถวายบังคมไท่หวงไท่โฮ่ว
I shall take my leave now.
เช่นนั้นเจ๋อหนิงขอทูลลาเพคะ
Let me see you off.
ข้าจะไปส่งเจ้า
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
Come.
มา
Sit down.
นั่งสิ
Much obliged, Grand Empress Dowager.
ขอบพระทัยเพคะไท่หวงไท่โฮ่ว
Cutting down the quota of Shencai Army's recruitment?
ลดจำนวนพลของทัพเสินไฉ
Yes.
ขอรับ
Li Deyun has been discussing it
นี่คือเรื่องที่หลายวันนี้หลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
with his scholars
ปรึกษากับลูกศิษย์ของเขาขอรับ
Great.
ดี
While I was meditating in isolation,
ฉวยโอกาสที่ข้าปิดด่าน
these mindless clowns
ดูท่าเหล่าคนชั่วกำเริบเสิบสาน
were having the time of their life.
จะวิ่งเต้นกันสนุกเชียว
Sir.
ใต้เท้า
The eunuchs
กงกงหลายท่าน
are awaiting your decision.
ล้วนรอการตัดสินใจของท่าน
How should we stop their plan?
ว่าควรยับยั้งเรื่องนี้อย่างไรขอรับ
No.
ไม่
Let them do as they please.
ปล่อยเขาไป
Months' worth
ก่อนหน้านี้
of the military pay was embezzled.
เบี้ยเลี้ยงขาดไปหลายเดือนไม่ใช่หรือ
Send out the words.
ปล่อยข่าวออกไป
Tell the people Li Deyun fills his own pocket with the money.
บอกว่าหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋นยักยอก
Not only is he corrupted,
ไม่เพียงแค่นี้
but he is also going to cut down
เขายังต้องการรุกไปอีกก้าว
the provision supplies.
ด้วยการตัดทอนเสบียงอีก
But doing so
เมื่อเป็นเช่นนี้
might cause an uproar in the army.
เกรงว่าในกองทัพต้องเกิดปัญหาแน่ขอรับ
Then so be it.
ก็ให้พวกเขาทะเลาะกันไปสิ
It is time to get rid
ถึงเวลาต้องถอน
of this pain in the neck named Li Deyun.
หนามตำตาเช่นหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋นแล้ว
Yes.
ขอรับ
Where is Cheng Xi?
เฉิงซีอยู่ที่ใด
In the ninth cell.
ห้องขังหมายเลขเก้าขอรับ
What message
ฝ่าบาท
did Your Majesty ask Li Zening to deliver?
ให้หลี่เจ๋อหนิงถ่ายทอดคำพูดใดเพคะ
What about you?
เจ้าล่ะ
What did you and my uncle
ในวันแต่งงาน
come up with before
เจ้ากับเสด็จอาปรึกษากันเรื่องแผนใด
Without a Crown Prince,
ฝ่าบาทไม่มีรัชทายาท
your life will be at risk.
อันตรายยิ่ง
Indeed.
ก็จริง
So Your Majesty and Official Li
ดังนั้นฝ่าบาทกับใต้เท้าหลี่
must proceed with haste.
ต้องรีบดำเนินการแล้วเพคะ
What is your guess?
เช่นนั้นเจ้าเดาอะไรได้
Nothing at all.
หม่อมฉันไม่ได้เดาอะไรได้
However,
เพียงแต่
Your Majesty are an Emperor.
ฝ่าบาททรงเป็นโอรสสวรรค์
You must carry out the way of Heaven.
ควรตามมติสวรรค์
Why did the late emperor fail?
รู้หรือไม่ว่าเหตุใดอดีตฮ่องเต้จึงพ่ายแพ้
The Morning Dew Rebellion was a conspiracy.
เป็นเพราะแผนเจาลู่เป็นแผนร้าย
It wasn't the way of Heaven.
ไม่ใช่เจตจำนงแห่งสวรรค์
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
The time has come.
โอกาสมาถึงแล้ว
There is no Empress Regent.
ไม่มีการว่าราชการหลังม่าน
There are no shady dealings.
ไม่มีลอบทำเรื่องน่าละอายใจ
In the new game of chess,
ในหมากกระดานใหม่นี้
you are the overseer
พระองค์ทรงเป็น
for both Prince Guang and I.
ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกของหม่อมฉันกับอ๋องกวง
For this round,
หมากกระดานนี้
you and Qiu Ziliang
เป็นพระองค์กับฉิวจื่อเหลียง
will battle each other fair and square.
ดวลกันอย่างผ่าเผยเพคะ
You must feel curious
เห็นข้า
upon seeing me again.
แปลกใจมากใช่หรือไม่
You finished your isolated meditation.
การปิดด่านของเจ้ายุติแล้วหรือ
Yes.
ใช่แล้ว
I was in isolated meditation
ที่ปิดด่านก็เพราะ
because there were things I couldn't fathom.
มีบางเรื่องที่ยังคิดไม่เข้าใจ
But everything is clear to me now.
ตอนนี้คิดจนแจ่มชัดแล้ว
So I came out.
ย่อมต้องออกมาสิ
I never thought
คิดไม่ถึงเลย
you were Qi Qing's daughter.
ว่าเจ้าจะเป็นบุตรีของฉีชิง
After Qi Qing's failed coup,
หลังฉีชิงก่อกบฏล้มเหลว
you were exiled to a foreign land,
เจ้าก็ระหกระเหินไปต่างถิ่น
and saved by Cheng Huaizhi.
ได้เฉิงหวายจื้อช่วยไว้
You followed Cheng Huaizhi
จากนั้นก็ติดตามเฉิงหวายจื้อ
to Heng'an.
มาถึงเหิงอันด้วยกัน
You talked Cheng Huaizhi into
เจ้ายุยงเฉิงหวายจื้อ
working as a eunuch
ให้ขายตัวเข้าวัง
so you and your half brother, Prince Guang
ก็เพื่อเข้ามาพบกับอ๋องกวง
from a different father
น้องชายร่วมมารดา
could reunite.
ต่างบิดรของเจ้าผู้นั้น
From there on,
นับจากนั้น
you had been plotting to help Prince Guang ascend to the throne.
เจ้าก็วางแผนให้อ๋องกวงครองราชย์
After the Morning Dew Rebellion,
หลังจากกบฏเจาลู่
you instigated Emperor Wenzong
เจ้าก็ยุยงให้เหวินจง
to pass the throne to Prince Guang.
สืบทอดบัลลังก์ให้อ๋องกวง
As you wished, Emperor Wenzong wrote a posthumous edict.
เหวินจงเขียนพินัยกรรมตามที่เจ้าปรารถนา
He ordered Han Yue to pass it to Wang Yang.
สั่งหานเยว่นำไปมอบให้หวังหยาง
But I was one step ahead of you.
ข้าเร็วกว่าเจ้าก้าวหนึ่ง
I raided the Wang family's house.
ยึดตระกูลหวัง
I killed Wang Yang.
สังหารหวังหยาง
By the time you arrived,
เมื่อเจ้าไปถึงที่นั่น
the edict was nowhere to be found.
พินัยกรรมก็หายสาบสูญไปแล้ว
Prince Guang found out
อ๋องกวงพบว่า
that Wang Yang's youngest granddaughter survived the attack.
หลานคนเล็กของหวังหยางยังไม่ตาย
He took her in.
จึงนำนางกลับไป
After many considerations,
คิดไปคิดมา
he decided to hide her
สุดท้ายก็ยังนำนาง
inside the Violet Bureau.
ไปซ่อนที่หน่วยอาภรณ์ม่วง
You thought the Little Fish
เจ้าคิดว่าเด็กหญิงคนนั้น
could restrain Qi Yan,
จะตรึงฉีเยี่ยนเอาไว้ได้
so you agreed with the plan.
ก็เลยเห็นด้วยอย่างยินดี
You even forged a new identity for her.
ทั้งยังช่วยนางสร้างฐานะปลอม
You gave her the name "Cheng Ruoyu."
เปลี่ยนชื่อเป็นเฉิงรั่วอวี๋
- You knew everything. - Of course.
- เจ้ารู้หมดทุกอย่างแล้ว - แน่นอน
If there is anything I want to know,
ขอเพียงเป็นสิ่งที่ข้าอยากรู้
I will know.
ข้าก็ต้องรู้ได้หมด
But you, on the other hand,
แต่เจ้า
were kept in the dark.
มีสิ่งที่ไม่รู้
Your beloved brother
น้องชายคนดีของเจ้า
never told you
ต้องไม่ได้บอกเจ้าแน่
Wang Ruoling wasn't the sole survivor.
ไม่เพียงแค่หวังรั่วหลิง
Her older sister Wang Ruoqing
แต่ยังมีพี่สาวของนางหวังรั่วชิง
was also alive and well.
ต่างก็มีชีวิตอยู่อย่างสุขสบายดี
Wang Ruoqing lives?
หวังรั่วชิงยังไม่ตายหรือ
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
Yanzhi is Wang Ruoqing.
เยียนจือก็คือหวังรั่วชิง
is Wang Ruoqing.
คือหวังรั่วชิง
She's Yu'er sister.
เป็นพี่สาวแท้ ๆ ของอวี๋เอ๋อร์
You set Cheng Ruoyu
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋กับฉีเยี่ยน
and Qi Yan up.
ที่เจ้าวางแผนไว้ก่อนหน้านี้
What if it was Cheng Ruoyu and Yanzhi?
หากบอกว่าเป็นเฉิงรั่วอวี๋กับเยียนจือ
Wouldn't they
คู่นี้เล่า
make the story more interesting?
จะน่าสนใจกว่าหรือไม่เล่า
What do you want?
เจ้าคิดจะทำอะไร
I bet you couldn't swallow
ก่อนหน้านี้เจ้าต้องพ่ายแพ้อย่าง
your disgraceful defeat.
ไม่ยินยอมพร้อมใจมากแน่
Would you care for another round?
อยากจะเล่นอีกสักครั้งหรือไม่
Let's make Wang Ruoling and Wang Ruoqing
ให้หวังรั่วหลิงกับหวังรั่วชิง
be at each other's throat.
ต่อสู้กันสักตั้ง
Ruoling.
รั่วหลิง
Yan Xiu.
เหยียนซิว
What would make the Left Advisor
เกิดเรื่องอะไรขึ้นกันแน่
come here in person?
ถึงกับทำให้จั่วเชอต้องออกโรงเอง
I was ordered by the Chess Overseer
ข้าได้รับคำสั่งท่านผู้นำสำนักหมากรุก
to keep you safe.
มาคุ้มครองเจ้า
Follow me to another path.
เจ้าตามข้าเปลี่ยนเส้นทางเถอะ
Do not go to Jiannan.
อย่าไปเจี้ยนหนานเลย
I don't need your protection.
ข้าไม่ต้องการให้เจ้าคุ้มครอง
I'm not changing my destination.
และจะไม่เปลี่ยนเส้นทางด้วย
I only want
ข้าเพียงแค่อยาก
to take you to safety.
นำเจ้าไปสถานที่ปลอดภัย
Stop following me.
จะให้ดีเจ้าก็อย่าตามข้ามา
Otherwise, you will face my wrath.
ไม่เช่นนั้น อย่าหาว่าข้าไม่เกรงใจ
Ruoling!
รั่วหลิง
- Come out! - Aunt.
เจ้าออกมานะ ท่านอาหญิง
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
You are in grave danger!
ตอนนี้เจ้าอันตรายมากนะรู้หรือไม่
I just want to keep you safe!
ข้าแค่อยากคุ้มครองเจ้าจริง ๆ
Aunt!
ท่านอาหญิง
What's wrong with you?
ท่านเป็นอะไรไป
Are you hurt or is it...
ท่านบาดเจ็บอยู่ ยังต้อง...
I'll live.
ไม่ตายหรอก
I didn't come for you.
ข้าเองก็ไม่ได้มาหาเจ้า
Since you're safe,
ในเมื่อเจ้าไม่เป็นอะไร
I have nothing to worry about.
เช่นนั้นข้าก็สบายใจแล้ว
Where are you going?
เช่นนั้นท่านจะไปไหนหรือ
I'm sending Li Rong's ashes
ข้าจะนำอัฐิของลี่หรง
back to her home.
ส่งกลับบ้านเกิดนาง
So...
เช่นนั้น
Did you give up on your obsession?
ท่านเลิกหมกมุ่นแล้วหรือ
I'm just a useless woman.
ตอนนี้ข้าก็เป็นเพียงคนพิการคนหนึ่ง
I have no obsession anymore.
ยังจะหมกมุ่นอะไรได้อีก
Aunt.
ท่านอาหญิง
Perhaps
ถ้าอย่างไร
I could escort you there.
ข้าจะไปส่งท่านแล้วกัน
Never mind.
ไม่ต้องหรอก
I'm heading for Dongchuan.
ข้ากำลังจะไปตงชวนพอดี
It's on the way to Madam Li's hometown.
เป็นทางเดียวกับบ้านเก่าท่านอาลี่
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
Thank you.
ขอบใจเจ้ามาก
But after what we went through,
แต่ผ่านเรื่องราวมามากขนาดนี้
I can't bring myself
ข้าจนปัญญา
to be so intimate with you.
จะอยู่ร่วมกับเจ้าให้ดีแล้ว
We should go our separate ways.
พวกเราแยกทางกันเดินเถอะ
♪Life is a dream, how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪